<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The description of fleshly lusts. Or a profitable and fruitfull sermon vpon the first Epistle of Saint Peter, Chap. 2. vers. 11. 12. Preached and penned by that famous, learned, iudicious, orthodoxall, holy, wise, and skilfull preacher and servant of God, now deceased, and with his God triumphing in Heaven, Iohn Randall, Batchelour of Divinitie, pastour of St. Andrewes Hubbart in little East cheape London, sometimes fellow of Lincolne Coledge in Oxford. And now published, to the glory of God, the edification of his church, and the honourable memoriall of the author, by William Holbrooke, preacher of the word of God in the church aforesaid</title>
            <author>Randall, John, 1570-1622.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10391</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20669</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102397</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838182</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838182</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2547</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10391)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2547)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1078:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The description of fleshly lusts. Or a profitable and fruitfull sermon vpon the first Epistle of Saint Peter, Chap. 2. vers. 11. 12. Preached and penned by that famous, learned, iudicious, orthodoxall, holy, wise, and skilfull preacher and servant of God, now deceased, and with his God triumphing in Heaven, Iohn Randall, Batchelour of Divinitie, pastour of St. Andrewes Hubbart in little East cheape London, sometimes fellow of Lincolne Coledge in Oxford. And now published, to the glory of God, the edification of his church, and the honourable memoriall of the author, by William Holbrooke, preacher of the word of God in the church aforesaid</title>
                  <author>Randall, John, 1570-1622.</author>
                  <author>Holbrooke, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. D[awson] for Nathaniel Newbery and William Sheffard, and are to be sold at their shops in Popes-heads Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2547:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DESCRIPTION OF FLESHLY LVSTS.</p>
            <p>OR A PROFITABLE AND FRVITFVLL SERMON Vpon the firſt Epiſtle of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> Chap. 2. verſ. 11.12. Preached and Penned by that famous, learned, iudicious, Orthodoxall, holy, wiſe, and skilfull Preacher and ſervant of God, now deceaſed, and with his God triumphing in Heaven, IOHN RANDALL, Batchelour of Divinitie, Paſtour of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Andrewes Hubbart</hi> in little <hi>Eaſt-cheape</hi> LONDON, Sometimes Fellow of <hi>Lincolne</hi> Colledge in OXFORD.</p>
            <p>And now publiſhed, to the glory of God, <hi>the edification of his Church, and the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Memoriall of the Author, by</hi> WILLIAM HOLBROOKE, Preacher of the Word of God in <hi>the Church aforeſaid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Newbery</hi> and <hi>William Sheffard,</hi> and are to be ſold at their Shops in <hi>Popes</hi>-head Alley. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2547:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2547:2"/>
            <head>TO THE VVORTHY AND TRVLY RELIGI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVS LADY, THE LADY WELD, ALL BLESSINGS internall, and externall, ſpirituall and <hi>bodily in this life, and eternall Glory in the world to come, be multiplied.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>WORTHY LADY,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the promiſe and worde of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note> that he will honor them that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him, which extendeth it ſelfe not onely to the time of this life, but to the time of death and after alſo: this promiſe it is our part and duty to verifie and make good to, and vpon the heads of all the people of God, both
<pb facs="tcp:2547:3"/> in the time of their life, death, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, that ſo God may be found true in his promiſe, and to doe what hee hath ſayd; This is done of vs, as by many wayes, ſo by keeping and being meanes of preſerving an honorable memoriall of them, that therein they may for ever be bleſſed and honorable, according to that of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 10.7.</note> 
               <hi>The memoriall of the iuſt ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 112.6.</note> and that of the Prophet <hi>David, The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance,</hi> The conſideration whereof mooved mee to thinke and conſider with my ſelfe, how I might performe this duty to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of this following Sermon, which whileſt I thought vpon, I ſaw no better meanes to performe it by, then by publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome of his worthy labours, that ſo (by,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.4.</note> and in them) he might liue and ſpeake, though he bee dead, as it is ſayd of <hi>Abell,</hi> and be had in everlaſting and honourable remembrance to the ende of the worlde. For which ende, next to Gods glory, and the good of his Church, I haue publiſhed (for the preſent) two Sermons given me, by his Executors, which I found in his Study,
<pb facs="tcp:2547:3"/> perfected, and written with his own hand faire and legible, aboue any thing which yet I find of his, as if he had purpoſed them for the Preſſe, and had fitted them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto: one of which Sermons is this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which I make bolde to offer to the view of the World, vnder the protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your Ladiſhip. It needeth not a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or Epiſtle of Recommendation from me or any other, it is able enough, and will ſpeake for it ſelfe, both for Method and Matter, wherein, I dare ſay, as the Text is Methodically, genuinely, and naturally handled, ſo the matter is worthy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, and divers paſſages therein not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, and no wonder, ſeeing it is the worke of a skilfull Workeman, who was more then ordinarily gifted from God, and fitted for the Worke of the Miniſtery, which the Lord appoynted him vnto. The reaſon why I attempt the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this Dutie firſt to him, is this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was one that loved me dearely in his life time, yea, honoured me much by his high eſteeme, &amp; reverent ſpeech to all, of me, and his countenancing and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging
<pb facs="tcp:2547:4"/> me in the worke of my Miniſtery, for the ſpace of nine yeares laſt paſt; during all which time, I exerciſed my Miniſtery in his charge, with great approbation from him, and comfort to him, as he often con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed; ſo that I had reaſon to be firſt in this worke, and <hi>(lege talionis)</hi> to honour him that honoured me I haue made bolde, and beene moved to Dedicate this Sermon to your Ladiſhip for two reaſons eſpecially, firſt, becauſe of that honourable eſteeme and reſpect, which, I know, is ſeated in your religious heart, to all the faithfull Miniſters of God, and was to the Author of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in particular and ſpeciall, whereupon I perſwade my ſelfe, that you will eſteeme and reſpect a Fatherles childe of his, now tendered vnto you, by me, (a friend to the dead and the living) and affoord it all the countenance you can, by kinde receiuing of it, and other wayes, as you would haue done to the Author of it, whom you oft deſired to haue bin familiarly acquainted with, and to haue entertained, as you long haue done, and ſtill doe, many of Gods faithfull Miniſters and Servants. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb facs="tcp:2547:4"/> reaſon is, that I might take occaſion hereby, publiquely to acknowledge my vnfained thankfulneſſe to your Ladiſhip, for all the kindneſſes, you haue ſhewed and done to me and mine.</p>
            <p>This I thought to haue acknowledged long before this time, by publiſhing ſome worke of my owne, and dedicating it to your <hi>Ladiſhip,</hi> but haue hitherto kept back, for divers reaſons known to my ſelfe, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, continuing my reſolution ſo to doe, if God will and permit life and opportunity. Having thus rendred my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why I dedicate this little worke to your <hi>Ladyſhip,</hi> I beſeech you accept them for excuſe of my boldnes in ſo doing, and accept this worke as the labour, yea the childe of a faithfull ſervant of God, and one that put vp many a hearty prayer to God for you, eſpecially conſidering, it will requite all the countenance you can ſhew it, by the good which (through Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) it will doe to your Soule, which I heartily wiſh to your <hi>Ladyſhip,</hi> and all that ſhall reade it, from him that is able with the ſhowers of his grace to make it fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:2547:5"/> to you and them.<note place="margin">Pro. 10.22.</note> His bleſſing onely maketh rich both for Soule and Body; without his bleſſing wee Preach, and Print, and the people heare and reade, in vaine. To him that is the onely true God, one in Eſſence, three in Perſon, I doe, and dayly will, commend your <hi>Ladyſhip,</hi> in my dayly prayers, for attaynement of all needefull bleſſings for Soule and body in this life, and eternall Glory in the world to come, through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt; In whom</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am, and ever will be at <hi>Your</hi> Ladyſhips <hi>Commaund in the worke of the Lord,</hi> WILLIAM HOLBROOKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2547:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE DESCRIPTION OF <hi>FLESHLY LVSTS.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 PETER, CHAP. 2. ver. 11. and 12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Dearely beloued, I beſeech you, as Strangers and Pilgrimes, to abſtaine from fleſhly luſts, which fight againſt the Soule: And haue your converſation ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Church of God, hauing ſuffered a great Eclipſe of her glory, having beene ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly diminiſhed by the falling away of the whole Nation of the Iewes, a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which the LORD had choſen peculiar to himſelfe, was ſoone after ſupplyed, partly, through the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> and partly, through the teaching and myracles of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, and partly, through the miniſtery of his Apoſtles and Diſciples, together with the happy ſucceſſe that God gaue thereunto; was, (I ſay) ſoone after ſupplied, and her breaches repaired and filled vp againe, by the converſion and calling of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. And becauſe the Gentiles ſhould not fall away as the Iewes had done before, (for it is the Apoſtles reaſon, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.21. If God ſpared not the naturall branches, much leſſe will he ſpare the wilde;) therefore the Apoſtles
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2547:6"/> vſed all diligence to confirme them in that faith which they had ſubſcribed vnto. For ſo it behooved the Lords husbandmen, not onely to plant, and ſo giue over, but alſo to water that which they had planted; not onely to ſow the ſeede of the Word in the hearts of men, and ſo leaue off, but alſo to carry a watchfull eye over it, ſtill che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing it vp, and preſerving it from being over-runne with weedes, or peſtered with other annoyances.</p>
            <p>Hence it was, that <hi>Paul</hi> having taken paines in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching to many particular Churches, did not ſo leaue them, but in a godly iealouſie over them writes Epiſtle after E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, ſometimes to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> ſometimes to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> ſometimes to the <hi>Theſſalonians, &amp;c.</hi> earneſtly ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing them to ſtand faſt in that faith which they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Hence it was that <hi>Iames</hi> having inſtructed the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the twelue Tribes in the faith of Chriſt, did not ſo leaue them, but ſeconds his preaching with an Epiſtle written to them for their confirmation in the faith. And hence it was that our Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> being the miniſter of the Circumciſion, as we reade, <hi>Galathians</hi> 2.7. having preached Chriſt to thoſe Gentiles that firſt had beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to the profeſſion of the Iewes, and afterward from the Iewes profeſſion to the faith of Chriſt, did not ſo leaue them; but writes this and his other Epiſtle generall to them all, as they were diſperſed in divers places of the world; exhorting them hereby to walke worthy of that vocation and holy profeſſion which they had taken vpon them: and having firſt ſhewed, <hi>Chapter</hi> 1 <hi>verſe</hi> 2. the great mercy of God towards them in electing them to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion through Ieſus Chriſt, hee doth thence inforce an exhortation, <hi>verſe</hi> 13.14.15. of that Chapter, that they muſt be holy, becauſe God who is their father and hath choſen them, is holy: And having ſhewed them ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty their Redemption, <hi>verſe</hi> 18.19. that it was not made with gold nor ſilver, but with the pretious blood of that immaculate Lambe Chriſt Ieſus; hee doth thence inferre another exhortation in the beginning of this 2. <hi>chap.</hi> that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2547:6"/> ſeeing they are ſo pretiouſly bought, therefore they muſt lay aſide all maliciouſnes, and diſſimulation, and envie, and evill ſpeaking, and as new borne babes &amp;c. And thirdly having amplified the great bountifulnes of God towards them, partly by comparing them with others <hi>ver.</hi> 7.8.9. that whereas Chriſt was made to others a ſtone to ſtumble at, and a rocke of offence, yet vnto theſe he was an elect and pretious ſtone, whereby they were knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Lords building: and partly by comparing their preſent eſtate of grace with their former eſtate of nature, <hi>verſe</hi> 9.10. that whereas before, they had lien in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, now they were called to a marvellous light; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in times paſt they were no people, now they are the people of God; in times paſt they were not vnder mercy, but now they haue obtained mercy; hee doth thence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, as it were by force of conſequence this third exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation which I haue now read vnto you: The Summe whereof is briefly this, to perſwade thoſe Chriſtians to holineſſe of life: and as holineſſe of life hath two partes, ſo this exhortation conſiſts of two branches anſwerable thereunto. The firſt part of an holy life is The Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and ſubduing of the luſts of the fleſh; and to this hee exhorts vs in the firſt branch of this Scripture, <hi>verſe</hi> 11. <hi>I beſeech you Brethren abſtaine from &amp;c.</hi> The ſecond part of an holy life is the honeſt converſation and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of our ſelues in the world, and to this hee exhorts vs in the ſecond branch of of this Scripture, <hi>verſe</hi> 12. <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving your converſation honeſt, &amp;c.</hi> In the firſt branch, that is, <hi>verſe</hi> 11. wee may obſerue firſt the matter it ſelfe, <hi>Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from fleſhly luſts;</hi> and ſecondly the Apoſtles enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of this matter vpon them, vſing two motiues or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements to perſwade them to it: The firſt motiue is drawne <hi>à conditione fidelium,</hi> from the eſtate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods Children in this life, they are <hi>Strangers and Pilgrimes;</hi> the ſecond motiue is drawne <hi>à naturâ concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiae,</hi> from the nature of theſe luſtes <hi>they fight againſt the Soule.</hi> But yet to faſten the whole body of this exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2547:7"/> vpon them the rather, hee vſeth here two covert Inſinuations: firſt, hee cloſes with them by a terme of loue and kindnes, hee cals them his dearely beloved: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that he may the better prevayle with them, hee deales by humble entreatie, hee beſeeches them; <hi>Dearely beloved, I beſeech you.</hi> But before I come to handle either the partes or the Inſinuations, I muſt obſerue out of the coherence or agreement of this with that which went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, one profitable note for our Inſtruction.</p>
            <p>Seeing the Apoſtle doth here inferre this exhortation vpon the rehearſall of Gods bleſſings beſtowed vpon his people, as if, becauſe God had ſo loved them, therfore they were bound to performe this dutie towards him, hence I note vnto you, that every bleſſing and mercy that God vouchſafeth vnto vs, doth effectually call vpon vs to liue in the feare and obedience of God.</p>
            <p>For as <hi>Iſaac</hi> dealt with his Sonne <hi>Iacob Gen.</hi> 28.1. hee bleſſed him, and he charged him, ſayth the Text, hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed a bleſſing vpon him, and withall he charged him to performe a duty: even ſo doth the Lord with his Children; hee giues them bleſſings, hee beſtowes mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies vpon them, but ſo, that every bleſſing and favour which the Lord beſtowes vpon them, doth exact and call for a duty that they muſt performe towards him.</p>
            <p>In the 5. <hi>chap.</hi> of <hi>Eſay, verſe</hi> 1.2. the Lord had done much for his Vineyard; it was planted on a very fruitfull hill, hee hedged it, hee gathered out the ſtones of it, hee planted it with the beſt plants, hee built a Towre in the midſt of it, and made a winepreſſe therein: and what then? did he all this for nothing? No; the Text ſayth Then hee looked that it ſhould bring forth grapes; as if the Prophet ſhould ſay, becauſe the Lord had done ſo much for his Vineyard; therefore hee expected, and great cauſe there was that it ſhould bring foorth good ſtore of good grapes. And this the Lord himſelfe would teach vs by the words of his owne mouth: For in <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.2. The Lord being to deliver his Law to his people,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2547:7"/> telles them firſt, that he is the Lord their God, which brought them out of the Land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> out of the houſe of bondage; vſing the rehearſall of his goodneſſe towards them, as a moſt effectuall bond and perſwaſion to tye them to the obedience of his Law. For thus it was even from the firſt bleſſing that ever God beſtowed vpon man, there enſued a Commandement vpon it, as we reade, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.15.16. that the Lord placed <hi>Adam</hi> in the Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> and withall gaue him Commandement, that he ſhould ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from the forbidden fruit. Here then we ſee (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) the right and true vſe of the bleſſings of God vpon vs; ſo many mercies as he ſhews vnto vs, we muſt eſteeme to be ſo many ſpurres, to pricke vs forward to well doing; and to be ſo many Meſſengers ſent vnto vs from God, to call vpon vs for the due performance of all ſuch Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Duties, as belong to our ſeverall callings. Satan him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, though a malicious depraver and abuſer of all Gods bleſſings towards vs, yet doth acknowledge to Gods owne face, that his bleſſings do exact a dutie at our hands, Doth <hi>Iob</hi> ſerue God for nought? ſaith he, <hi>Iob</hi> 1.9. As if Satan ſhould haue ſaid; It is true indeed, that <hi>Iob</hi> is an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and iuſt man, one that feares God, and eſchewes euill; but doth he ſo for nought? No, he hath great reaſon for it; For thou haſt made an hedge about him, and about all that he hath on euery ſide. Now (Beloued) if Satan thought it reaſon that <hi>Iob</hi> ſhould ſerue God, becauſe God had bleſſed <hi>Iob;</hi> oh, how wicked is our ingratitude, if, when we haue receiued fauours and bleſſings at Gods hands, (as we doe receiue daily) we doe not in lieu and requitall thereof apply our ſelues to Gods ſeruice? The Apoſtle in the twelfth to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> ver. 1. hath giuen vs an excellent Preſident in this caſe: <hi>I beſeech you,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>by the mercies of God, that you giue vp your bodies a liuing ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, holy, and acceptable vnto God:</hi> He hath no better meanes to adiure vs, as it were, and to bind vs to offer vp our ſelues a liuing ſacrifice vnto God, then the mercies and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours which he hath beſtowed vpon vs.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2547:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2547:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:2547:9"/>
            <p>To apply this preſent caſe more particularly to our ſelues, conſider aright, I beſeech you, the caſe of theſe faithfull, to whom the Apoſtle makes this Exhortation; and when you haue compared their caſe with your owne caſe, then tell me, if this ſame Exhortation may not as juſtly, nay, much more juſtly be enforced vpon vs. Theſe were Gentiles, and ſo are we; theſe had ſitten in darknes, and ſo did we; theſe were aliants from the covenant, and ſo were we; but God had choſen them a peculiar people to himſelfe, and ſo he hath choſen vs; he brought them into a marveilous light, and ſo he hath done by vs; he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them to the knowledge of his truth, and ſo he hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs; he redeemed them with the precious bloud of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and ſo he hath redeemed vs; he regenerated them by his ſpirit, and ſo he hath done vs; therefore this Dutie lies as hard vpon vs as vpon them, and this ſame Exhortation is to be preſt as forcibly vpon vs as vpon them; wherefore, <hi>Dearely Beloved, I beſeech you as ſtrangers and Pilgrims, to abſtaine from fleſhly luſts, which fight againſt the ſoule.</hi> Nay, to goe a little further in this application, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath gone a great deale further in bleſſing vs: they were but young Novices in the Faith, as it ſeemes to be implied in the ſecond verſe of this Chapter, <hi>New borne babes;</hi> but we haue beene long trained vp in the knowledge, his bleſſed Goſpell hauing had free paſſage amongſt vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue theſe fortie yeares: they were diſperſed abroad in the world, as appeares Chapter 1. verſ. 1. and ſcattered here and there, but we enioy the Communion of the Word &amp; Sacraments in the vnitie of this one particular Church; they were ſtrangers where they liued, but we ſit at home vnder our Vine, and vnder our Fig-tree, as the Prophet ſpeakes, and Gods holy name be euerlaſtingly praiſed for it. We need not to gee begge the bread of life in forreine Nations, for we haue it brought home euen to our dores: much more iuſtly therefore doe theſe extraordinary bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of God bind vs to this Dutie, then theirs did them, and much more earneſtly muſt this Exhortation be enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2547:9"/> vpon vs then vpon them; wherefore, <hi>Dearely beloued, I beſeech you;</hi> you that haue receiued this full meaſure of loue and mercy at Gods hands, <hi>I beſeech you to abſtaine from fleſhly luſts which fight againſt the Soule.</hi> If we had giuen to him firſt, then theſe his bleſſings had beene but requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls of our former kindneſſe; but now ſeeing he hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs when we did not loue him, ſeeing he hath thus bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs of his owne free good will, oh, how ſtreightly doe theſe vndeſerued fauours of God exact this Chriſtian dutie at our hands, euen our holines of life; wherefore <hi>I beſeech you,</hi> nay, you muſt know that the loue of God doth beſeech you, or rather impoſe it vpon you as a neceſſary Dutie, to <hi>abſtaine from fleſhly luſts, &amp;c.</hi> And let this ſuffice to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued concerning this point. Now I come to the Inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and firſt of the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dearely Beloved,</hi> I call it an Inſinuation, becauſe the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle by this terme of Kindneſſe, doth artificially cloſe with them, and wind both himſelfe, and his Exhortation into their hearts. For commonly the nature of Man, when it is counſelled and adviſed by others, is wont ſtraight wayes to looke into the heart of his Counſellor, to ſearch out with what affection he ſpeakes it, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly as he findes the affection of his Counſellor, ſo will he eſteeme of his Counſell. If a man willes vs to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our manners, thereby vpbraiding vs with our faults, or bewraying any bitterneſſe againſt vs, we will reiect his counſell, though never ſo good: If a man adviſe vs to any good courſe, for his owne profit, or for ſome advantage that himſelfe may get by it, wee refuſe his adviſe, though never ſo profitable: but if once we be perſwaded, that he loues vs, and that for loue and good will he adviſes vs to any courſes, preſently we hearken to him, and embrace his counſell, and are willing and readie to put it in practiſe. Wherefore our Apoſtle deales very skilfully here with theſe Chriſtians, firſt, proteſting his deare and tender loue towards them, that he doth not counſell them to this for any ſhame he would bring vpon them, or for any van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2547:10"/> that hee ſhould procure to himſelfe, but meerely for his heartie loue and affection that he beares vnto them, therefore they are in no caſe, either to contemne it, or ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it, but rather to embrace it with all willingneſſe. And here is an excellent Rule for vs, to frame our counſels by; that whenſoever any of vs reprooues his brother for any ſinne, as for drunkenneſſe, ſwearing, vncleanneſſe, or any ſuch prophane carriage, and counſels him to amend it, we muſt take heed, that it come not from any gall or bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in our hearts, for then it marres our Exhortation, and hardens him more in his ſinne; but it muſt come from loue within vs, and that from a tender and deare loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, if ever we deſire that our counſell ſhould take effect with him in his heart, to the reformation of his life, and ſauing of his ſoule.</p>
            <p>Againe, in that he calls them here his <hi>Dearely beloued,</hi> here is another obſervation offered vnto vs. He had ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the former Verſes, that they were the dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God, and therefore here in this Verſe he is bolde to call them his <hi>Dearely beloued;</hi> for, ſeeing that Chriſt did loue them dearely, his Apoſtle muſt needs loue them dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly too. For the Lord neuer beſtowes his loue vpon any, but withall he beſtowes many amiable Graces vpon them, ſuch as may procure them loue and fauour amongſt men; I ſay not, amongſt carnall men, that cannot looke any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then vpon fleſh and bloud, nor yet amongſt worldly men, that onely loue thoſe that are like themſelues, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſpirituall men, ſuch as can diſcerne the louely gifts and graces of God, ſhining in a mans ſoule. Wee reade, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 39.3, 4. of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> that the Lord was with him; <hi>Putiphar</hi> ſeeing the loue of God vpon him, did ſet his loue vpon him too: and in the 21. verſe of that Chapter, the Maſter of the Priſon ſaw that the Lord loued <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and then he loued <hi>Ioſeph</hi> too; and in the 41. Chapter, the 39. Verſe, euen <hi>Pharaoh</hi> himſelfe ſaw that the ſpirit of God was in <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and therefore he fauoured him, and preferred him exceedingly. Thus was it alſo with Chriſt himſelfe,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2547:10"/> of whom we reade, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.52. that he grew in loue and fauour with God and with men; firſt, in fauour with God, and then with men; for men loued him becauſe God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him firſt. Here is then a perfect Rule, whereby to frame our loue towards men; if firſt we behold and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry in them certaine teſtimonies of the loue of God, then may we be bold alſo to ſet our deareſt loue and affection vpon them. Wee muſt take heed that we be not too light of our loue, in beſtowing it vpon euery one; for our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian loue is, and ought to be a well ſetled affection, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from a good ground, and therefore we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it eſpecially vpon thoſe whom we ſee the Lord hath peculiarly endued with his ſanctifying and ſauing grace: neither yet on the other ſide muſt we be too ſparing of our loue, in beſtowing it onely vpon ſome few, that fit our owne humor beſt, but as many as the Lord hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to admit into the boſome of his Church, and to call to the profeſſion of our Chriſtian Faith, (except we ſee in them ſome euident cauſe to the contrary, as that they are hypocrites, or yeeld any other manifeſt ſignes of impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) thoſe we muſt loue, as preſuming and well hoping, that God doth loue them.</p>
            <p>But howſoeuer the Apoſtle had many reſpects to draw his deareſt loue to theſe faithfull ones, partly, becauſe they were his brethren in the fleſh, but much rather, becauſe they were his brethren in the Lord, embracing the ſame faith, worſhipping the ſame God, regenerate by the ſame ſpirit, and liuing in the communion of one and the ſame myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call bodie; yet there was one reaſon further then all theſe, that inflamed his heart with moſt feruent loue towardes them aboue all other; and this was the charge which was giuen to him ouer them, that he ſhould be their Inſtructor, to Preach the Doctrine of ſaluation vnto them. For the Miniſteriall charge, which was aſſigned vnto <hi>Peter</hi> ouer the Circumciſion, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.7. did knit his heart vnto them, faſter then euer the heart of <hi>Ionathan</hi> was knit vnto the heart of <hi>Dauid;</hi> ſo that in this reſpect he might well call
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2547:11"/> them his <hi>dearely beloued.</hi> Wherein he giues an example to the Miniſters of God, teaching them how they ought to eſteeme the flocke of Chriſt, whereof the holy Ghoſt hath made them ouer-ſeers; that they muſt carry a loue and affection towards them, and that not any common loue, but ſuch as proceeds from the deareſt and the deepeſt ſeate of their hearts. Deare is that loue which muſt preuaile with vs ſo farre as to make vs to lay downe our liues for thoſe whom we doe loue; It is ſo deare, and ſuch a great loue, as that our Sauiour, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.13. telles vs, there can be no greater. Greater loue can no man ſhew then this, when a man beſtowes his life for his friends; and yet ſuch muſt be the loue of a Paſtor toward his flocke, euen to lay downe his life for them, as <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.11. A good Shepheard, &amp;c. Thus it was with <hi>Moſes;</hi> that would rather be blotted out of the Booke of life himſelfe, then that the wrath of the Lord ſhould be powred out vpon the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Exod. 32.32. And thus it was with <hi>Paul;</hi> that would wiſh himſelfe to be ſeperated from Chriſt for his brethren and kinſmen according to the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.3. And thus it was with the great Shepherd of our ſoules, Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who did lay downe his life for his Sheepe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelfe to all thoſe dangers, which by our ſinnes we had incurred: and thus it ought to be with all the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God; they muſt loue their ſeuerall Charges, euen vnto death, embracing them with their deareſt affection.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Inſinuation is in theſe words, <hi>I beſeech you.</hi> For although by that Apoſtolike authoritie which he had receiued, he might command them, yet he had rather to deale with them by entreatie, to beſeech them. For this was a courſe fitter for him, and fitter for them alſo. Fitter for him, as being a Miniſter of the Word; it is for a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to command, it is for a Miniſter to beſeech: and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for them: the young tenderlings of a Vine are to be handled gently and charily; and ſo theſe being but young Chriſtians, as hath beene alreadie ſhewed out of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Verſe, were to be mildly dealt withall.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2547:11"/>
            <p>In matters of Religion, though ſometimes men may be compelled by ſtrong hand, and by force, to obedience, yet the readieſt way, either to winne thoſe that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, or to conteine thoſe that are alreadie wonne, in the bond of obedience, is (for the moſt part) by fayre meanes, and by kind perſwaſions: <hi>Suadenda potius eſt pietas quàm cogenda,</hi> ſayth a learned Father, Sooner is godlineſſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened vpon vs by perſwaſion then by compulſion. And the very Heathen man <hi>Seneca</hi> could tell vs, that in good cauſes, <hi>Faciliùs ducimur quam trahimur,</hi> It is eaſier to lead vs on by kind entreatie, then to draw vs on by conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning meanes. Here then is controuled that imperious Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which raignes in the Chayre of the Romiſh Sea, that takes vpon him to commaund all the world. He challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth himſelfe to be Chriſts Vicar, and <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor; but whither he be either of them, let his commaunding courſes teſtifie. Chriſt ſayd, Learne of me, for I am meeke and lowly: What meekneſſe is there in him, that ſends forth his <hi>Mandamus,</hi> nothing but commands and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings to the people of God? And <hi>Peter,</hi> as you ſee here, beſeeches theſe Chriſtians to be adviſed by him: but he that challenges himſelfe to be <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor, lookes for it as a dutie, to be beſought and crouched vnto by others, but himſelfe will beſeech none. It may be, he ſucceedes him in place, though that may be queſtioned too; but in meekneſſe of Spirit, and the performance of his Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall function, he doth as farre degenerate from <hi>Peter,</hi> as euer that Idolatrous King <hi>Manaſſah</hi> did degenerate from the ſteppes of his good Father <hi>Hezekiah.</hi> And thus much of the Inſinuations.</p>
            <p>Now to the parts of the Exhortation; and firſt, of the former part, contained in the 11. Verſe, the mortifying and ſubduing of the luſts of the Fleſh. Firſt, of the matter it ſelfe, and ſecondly, of the motiues, whereby the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle enforces this Exhortation vpon them. Firſt, of the matter, <hi>To abſtaine from fleſhly luſts.</hi> By <hi>luſts</hi> we are here to vnderſtand, the diſpoſitions, or inclinations that are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2547:12"/> within vs: by the <hi>fleſh,</hi> wee are to vnderſtand, our whole nature, and whatſoeuer in vs is not regenerate by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God; all which muſt be abſtained from, they muſt be mortified and ſubdued within vs; according to that, <hi>Galatians</hi> the fift Chapter, verſ. 24. <hi>They that are Chriſts, haue crucified the fleſh, with the affections and luſts thereof;</hi> that is, they haue crucified their nature, and the diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their nature. Euery one of theſe words require a ſeuerall Diſcourſe; and therefore I will treate of them ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally, and firſt, of the <hi>luſts,</hi> ſecondly, of the <hi>fleſh,</hi> thirdly, of <hi>abſtaining.</hi> Firſt, of <hi>luſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God in the beginning created Man vpright in nature, and without any blemiſh: but becauſe Man was but a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and therefore could not haue all perfections in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the Lord God furniſhed him with an holy appetite and deſire, whereby he might be carried to ſeeke after God, in whom onely he might find and enioy all perfections. This the Serpent perceiuing, tooke occaſion hereby to ſollicite <hi>Eue,</hi> not to deſire to enioy God, but to deſire to become God; abuſing this affection that was giuen to Man to make him happie, and turning it to his vtter bane and deſtruction. The end which the Serpent propoſed to her, <hi>to be as God,</hi> was a thing much to be deſired; and the Inſtrument which he vſed, the Apple of the forbidden tree, was very pleaſant, and much alſo to be deſired, as is ſayd, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.6. and ſo the Serpent robbed the Woman, and robbed her Husband, and robbed all their Poſteritie, of that godly affection, that holy appetite and deſire, which the Lord had furniſhed Mans nature withall. Euer ſince which firſt peruerting of our will and deſire, partly, by the propagation of this infection from our Parents into vs, and partly, by the Iuſtice of God, which hath inflicted it vpon vs as a curſe of that firſt ſinne, all the whole many of vs are peruerted in our wills, and ſo corrupted in all our deſires, that now the inclinations of our nature are no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger deſires, as they were in the beginning, but they are luſts and concupiſcences, nothing els but lewd and inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2547:12"/> affections. For as a little Leauen leaueneth the whole lumpe, euen ſo this Luſt hath infected our whole nature, that now wee are but a maſſe, and a heape of Luſts. Looke into all our affections, they are nothing but Luſts: looke into all our actions, they are nothing but Luſts: looke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all our ſinnes, our originall ſinne is nothing but Luſt, as S. <hi>Iames</hi> teaches, Chapter 1. Verſ. 14. <hi>Euery man is temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he is drawne away by his owne Luſt:</hi> and Chap. 4. verſ. 1. <hi>Whence are warres and contentions? Are they not hence, euen of your Luſts?</hi> Our actuall ſinnes are nothing but luſts, as the Apoſtle ſhews, <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.19, 20. Where he calls the workes of the fleſh, the luſts of the fleſh; and the 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> Chapter 2. verſ. 16. <hi>Whatſoeuer is in the world, as the luſt of the eyes, the luſt of the fleſh, and pride of life,</hi> and this is a kind of luſt too. Looke into all the parts of our bodies, and powers of our ſoules; and you ſhall finde nothing but Luſts in them: our eyes Luſt after delightfull ſights, our eares Luſt after pleaſant ſounds, our ſtomackes after ſweete meates, our hearts Luſt after fooliſh vanities, and the very ſpirit that is within vs, ſayth the Apoſtle, Luſteth after enuie, <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.5. So then the Apoſtle here exhorting theſe Chriſtians to abſtaine from Luſts, hath choſen a moſt ſignificant and compendious word, to expreſſe his meaning, he bids them to abſtaine from Luſts.</p>
            <p>Wherein we may obſerue, firſt, that this is a generall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation from all kindes of ſinne, for Luſt is the generall name for them all; not onely againſt Adultery and Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, which is the moſt naturall meaning of Luſt, but againſt Pride, and Enuie, and Othes, and Blaſphemies, and euery other ſinne. For he would not haue the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God be free from one ſinne, and defile themſelues with another, free from Adultery, but defiled with Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, or free from Drunkenneſſe, but defiled with En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, but he would haue them to be entirely holy: and as in the firſt verſe of this chapter, he willed them to lay aſide all diſſimulation, all maliciouſneſſe, all euill ſpeaking; ſo here he willes them to abſtaine from all ſinne. What is it vnto
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2547:13"/> thy health, if thou be free from one diſeaſe, and thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy infected with another? thou art ſtill but a diſeaſed man: and what is it to the comelines of thy body, to haue a faire face, but to want the proportion of thy other limmes? Thou art ſtill but a deformed man: and what is it to the gracing of thy Soule in the ſight of God, to be cleare from one ſinne, ſo long as another ſinne raignes within thee? but if thou canſt ſweepe away theſe luſts which the Apoſtle here ſpeakes of, then thou art clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of all thy diſeaſes to bee a ſound Chriſtian, and ridd of all thy deformities, to be gratious and acceptable in the ſight of the Lord.</p>
            <p>But wee may take this exhortation to be more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; as if the Apoſtle ſhould counſell theſe Chriſtians to abſtaine eſpecially from ſuch luſts, as the Gentiles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom they liued, were addicted vnto, that if they were giuen to riot, theſe ſhould eſpecially endeuour themſelues to ſobrietie; if they were giuen to wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, theſe ſhould eſpecially labour to chaſtity; if they were giuen to malice, theſe ſhould eſpecially labour to be moſt kind and gentle; that, as it is in the 12. <hi>verſe,</hi> when they ſhould ſee the good examples of theſe Chriſtians, they might learne by them to be drawne from their ſins, and ſo glorifie God in the day of their viſitation. Or els wee may take the exhortation to bee yet more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; as if the Apoſtle ſhould here counſell them to enter into their owne hearts, and there to make iuſt tryall what ſpeciall ſinne they did feele to rage moſt within them, and thereof they ſhould eſpecially labour to purge themſelues; for commonly euery man, even the beſt of vs all, hath his proper ſinne, ſome one ſinne, and ſome another, raging within vs aboue the reſt; and I know not, whether this be that <hi>Malus Genius</hi> that evill Spirit, which, the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then ſay, takes poſſeſſion of euery man; but ſure I am, that it is the proper luſt of our owne Nature, whether cauſed by the infection of our Parents, or by the tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature of our complexions, or by ſome celeſtiall influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2547:13"/> in our conception or birth, or rather indeed wrought in vs by the power of Sathan, after wee are come into the world; it is, I ſay, the proper luſt of euery mans owne nature, whereby he is inclined to one vice more then to another. One hath a touch of Envie, another hath a touch of Lying, another hath a touch of evill ſpeaking; in one is a ſpice of pride, in another a ſpice of wantonnes, in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ſpice of covetouſneſſe, (I ſpeake euen of the beſt; for in others it is more then a touch or ſpice, it raignes in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:) in euery one a ſpeciall inclination to ſome one ſpeciall ſin; and this is that luſt which fights againſt euery ones Soule, after a ſpeciall maner, as here is implyed; and therefore hee would haue vs, as to abſtaine from all ſinnes, ſo to make ſpeciall proviſion againſt that ſpeciall Luſt which is moſt rife and buſie within vs. Aske thy owne Soule, and examine thy ſelfe well, whether thou art not more incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to one vice then to another; ſearch it out throughly in the bowels of thy Nature; and when thou haſt found what principall ſinne thou feeleſt the power of Sathan and the deſire of thy owne fleſh moſt often moving thee vnto, thou muſt conſider that this is that fleſhly luſt, which of all others fights moſt fiercely againſt thy Soule, and thou muſt know, that thou art bound to labour eſpecially againſt that luſt, refraining from all occaſions and meanes, which may any way tend to the cheriſhing of that ſinfull and wicked humour and luſt in thee.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Seeing he diſwades vs here from luſts, we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue that he would haue Chriſtians not onely to abſtaine from all ſinnes, but alſo from the luſts of ſinnes, that is, the very firſt motions and inclinations to ſinne, for if we doe not ſtop and drie vp the fountaine of Sinne, we ſhall hardly ſtay it in the Channels; If we would kill a Serpent, wee muſt cruſh him in the head: and if wee would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Sinne, wee muſt ſmother it in the very firſt concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. As <hi>David,</hi> when hee fought againſt <hi>Goliah,</hi> did ſmite that vncircumciſed Philiſtine in the forehead, and ſo ſlue him: euen ſo muſt wee deale with ſinne, wee muſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2547:14"/> ſmite it in the forehead, and deſtroy it in the firſt motion, and the firſt luſt that wee feele within vs. For ſo doe they that are Chriſts; as the Apoſtles ſhewes, <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.24. they crucifie the fleſh with the affections and luſtes thereof: they crucifie the fleſh; there the Tree of ſinne is taken downe: they crucifie the fleſh with the affections: there both the ſapp and the heart of ſinne are periſhed: they crucifie the fleſh with the affections and luſts thereof; there the roote and all is withered and quite dried vp. In the firſt <hi>chapt.</hi> of <hi>Exodus verſe</hi> 16. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> tooke this courſe to deſtroy the Male Children of the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> hee commaunded, that when their mothers had brought them forth, death ſhould bee their midwife, they ſhould preſently bee killed and made away as ſoone as ever they began to liue. Let vs learne <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his pollicy for a better practiſe; ſeeing wee are to ſubdue ſinne, let the midwife of ſinne bee the death of ſinne, as ſoone as ever wee feele it quicken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vs, and begin to liue, wee muſt preſently ſtop the firſt breath that ever it takes, and deſtroy it in the firſt motion. Learne we this ſame leſſon of our Saviour, In the 4. <hi>chap.</hi> of <hi>Luke, verſe</hi> 5. the Devill came to him, and ſhewed him all the Kingdomes of the world in a twinckling of an eye: it was onely a ſhew; but our Saviour could not abide a ſhewe of ſinne; it was but in the twinckling of an eye; but our Saviour could not abide one glimpſe of ſinne; it was (I ſay) but a moment of time; but our Saviour could not abide that temptatation ſhould liue ſo much as one moment of time, but ſo ſoone as ever it began to ſtirre and to moue, preſently hee deſtroyed it.</p>
            <p>Now as here is matter of exhortation, teaching vs to beware of the firſt motions of ſinne, ſo here is matter of reproofe of an errour in Popery, that denies theſe firſt motions of ſinne to bee any ſinnes at all: they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Luſt or Concupiſcene to bee the cauſe of ſinne, but that it ſhould be a ſinne of it ſelfe, this they will in no wiſe acknowledge.</p>
            <p>But if it be a ſinne to transgreſſe the Law of God, then
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2547:14"/> luſt muſt needs be ſinne: Now Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> telles vs, 1 Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, Chap. 3. verſ. 4. that ſinne is nothing elſe but the tranſgreſſion of the Law; and it appeares plainely out of <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7. that Luſt is the tranſgreſſion of the Law, for the Law ſayth, <hi>Thou ſhalt not luſt;</hi> ſo that Luſt muſt needs be ſinne. The Law requires that thou ſhouldeſt loue the Lord thy God with all thy thought, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.27. therefore if euer thy thought be enclined to ſinne, (as Luſt takes her firſt hold in our thought) thou haſt tranſgreſſed the Law, and ſinned againſt God. It was but a flying thought which the Devill ſuggeſted into the hearts of the Scribes, that Chriſt blaſphemed when he ſayd to the ſicke of the Palſie, Thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee: for ſo wee reade <hi>Mark.</hi> 2.6. they onely reaſoned ſo in their hearts, as if they did not throughly conſent vnto it, but it was onely a conceit that runne in their heads; and yet our Sauiour checkes them for it, and calles it by the name of euill, as appeares <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Why thinke you euill in your hearts?</hi> And if it be euill, conſequently it muſt needs be ſinne. How light ſoeuer theſe men make of Concupiſcence, or Luſt, I am ſure that <hi>Paul</hi> felt by his owne experience, and to his great griefe acknowledged it to be ſinne, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.20. Not I, ſayth he, but ſinne that dwelleth in me. Their anſwere which here they alledge, that Luſt is indeed ſinne, yet not properly, but onely after a kinde of improper ſenſe; if <hi>Salomon</hi> ſhould heare it, he would condemne them of fooliſhneſſe; The foole, ſayth he, <hi>Prou.</hi> 14.9. makes a toy of ſinne: and ſurely, it is great fooliſhneſſe, to make ſo ſmall account of Luſt, and to eſteeme ſo light of ſinne, and to vſe ſuch a toyiſh and frivolous diſtinction in ſuch an earneſt and ſerious matter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Now concerning the <hi>fleſh,</hi> which is the ſecond thing here to be ſpoken of. By the name of <hi>fleſh,</hi> we are here to vnderſtand our whole nature: for as Luſt is moſt proper to one ſinne aboue the reſt, as namely, to Adultery, yet is it rightly applied to all ſinnes, becauſe euery ſinne is a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2547:15"/> Luſt; ſo the <hi>fleſh</hi> doth moſt properly ſignifie our matter, our carnall and bodily part, as it is oppoſed againſt our ſoule, or ſpirituall part, yet is it rightly extended to our whole nature, both of ſoule and bodie, except we be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate and borne anew; ſo that whatſoeuer is in vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate, it is here called by the name of fleſh. For ſo it is taken, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.17. where Chriſt ſayth vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> fleſh and bloud hath not revealed this vnto thee; that is, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is in the nature of man, hath taught thee this, but it is the ſpeciall worke of the ſpirit of God. And in the 1. to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> Chap. 2. verſ. 4. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man; he ſayth not, the carnall man, but euen the whole nature of man, ſoule and all, is ſo darkened, that it cannot perceiue the things that are of God: and therefore the Apoſtle calls our whole man, <hi>Corpus peccati,</hi> The bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of ſinne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6. becauſe ſinne hath infected our whole man; nay, he calles it <hi>Corpus mortis,</hi> Rom. 7.24. The body of death, becauſe it is in it ſelfe wholly cut off from the life of God, wherewith we were quickened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our fall. The Reaſons why the vnregenerate man, and in the beſt of vs the vnregenerate part is called by the name of <hi>fleſh,</hi> as here in this place, are two.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe either they proceed meerely of the fleſh, or at leaſt are wrought by the fleſh. Some luſts proceed meerely of the fleſh: our originall ſinne, it is not to be thought to ariſe in our ſoule, for that is created holy, and infuſed holy from aboue into euery one of vs at our firſt quickening in our Mother; but it is the materiall part, the fleſh which we draw from our Parents, that is infected with ſinne in it ſelfe, and as ſoone as ever the ſoule is vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ioyned vnto it, it infects the ſoule alſo. As <hi>Coſbi</hi> the Midianitiſh Woman defiled <hi>Zimri</hi> the <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> by ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him, as we reade <hi>Numbers</hi> 25. And as <hi>Salomons</hi> wiues, ſtrange women, turned his heart after other Gods, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11.4. And ſo the fleſh which we receiue of our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, as ſoone as it is married, as it were, vnto the ſoule,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2547:15"/> as ſoone as they are knit into one nature, the fleſh by clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and embracing the ſoule, doth defile the ſoule, and turne it after carnall luſts: and when once this luſt, this originall infection hath ſeized vpon vs in body and ſoule too, then our nature is become like a fiery Furnace, that continually ſends forth many flames of Concupiſcence: it ſtill egges vs on and provokes vs vnto ſinne, as the wife of <hi>Putiphar</hi> did ſollicite <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> day by day to commit wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, and to ſinne againſt God. Other luſts, though they doe not ariſe out of the fleſh, yet they are wrought in vs by the fleſh: It is the olde pollicie of Satan, to ſeeke firſt to overcome the weakeſt, that afterward he may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome the ſtrongeſt; he ſet firſt vpon <hi>Eue,</hi> that ſo he might overcome <hi>Adam;</hi> and ſo ſtill he ſets firſt vpon our fleſh, which is the weakeſt and moſt inclinable to ſinne, that afterward he may overcome the ſpirit; which, if it were not for the perſwaſions and allurements of the fleſh, would withſtand ſinne. For the Devill could never doe any thing againſt vs, but that he findes fit matter in our fleſh to worke vpon. As our Sauiour ſpake of himſelfe, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.30. The Prince of this world commeth, and hee finds nothing in me; ſo if we had not any corruption in our owne fleſh, Satan could even hardly faſten any temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation vpon vs. No, Beloved, here that is verified which our Saviour ſpake in another caſe, <hi>Inimici hominis domeſtici eius;</hi> The enemies of a man are they that are of his owne houſhold: and that alſo which our Saviour proved by his owne experience; He that dippes his finger with me in the diſh, it is he that lifts vp his heele againſt me; euen the ſame fleſh which we nouriſh in our owne boſome, lifts vp it ſelfe againſt vs to deſtroy vs. Here then let the children of God learne hereby to beware of their owne fleſh; and whenſoever Satan tempts thee, take heed, that thy owne fleſh doe not play the traytor with thee, and deliver thee over into the will and power of thine enemies. And let this kindle in every one of vs, a ſerious deſire to be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of this earthly Tabernacle which we beare about
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2547:16"/> vs; and to be ridde from this treacherous enemy of our owne fleſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond Reaſon, why the luſts of the vnregenerate are called after the name of fleſh, is, becauſe they tend to the cheriſhing of the fleſh, the carnall or naturall part. For, why doth the Epicure wallow vp and downe in all licentiouſneſſe, and the Voluptuous man ſell himſelfe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to the pleaſures of this life, and the Covetous man o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey his vnſatiable luſt and deſire of gaine, but that all thinges ſeeme to tend to the cheriſhing of their owne fleſh? I ſay, <hi>ſeeme to tend,</hi> becauſe it is but in appearance onely: for indeede, theſe things are ſo farre from cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing the fleſh, that contrariwiſe they are the very ſpoyle of our fleſh and decay of our Nature. Voluptuouſneſſe, is called by the Holy Ghoſt, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18. a ſinne againſt a mans owne body: Gluttony and Drunkenneſſe ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten mens liues and deforme their bodies, and marre their conſtitutions: and Covetouſneſſe waſts away a mans ſpirits, and ſokes vp the moiſture of Nature. Let this therefore teach vs to bee carefull and circumſpect that wee be not deceived by the outward appearance of ſinne, though it make never ſuch a goodly ſhew of cheriſhing our nature; ſeeing indeede it is the very bane of our nature, hurtfull to our bodies in this world, and the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſtruction both of Soule and Body in the world to come.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, wee are to ſpeake in one word concerning <hi>Abſtinence,</hi> which is the third point here to bee ſpoken of; <hi>Abſtaine from fleſhly luſts.</hi> As a carefull Phiſitian that is deſirous to recover the health of his patient, doth giue him ſpeciall charge to abſtaine from ſuch meates and drinkes as are enemies to his health; ſo the Apoſtle here wils this choſen people of God to abſtaine from fleſhly Luſtes, and to forbeare them as they loue their Soules health. In the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corint. chap.</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:2547:16"/> 25. The Apoſtles enforces this exhortation vpon vs by way of Compariſon: Every one that proveth Maſteries, (ſayth hee) abſtaines from all things that might bring his body out of temper; and this he doth for a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Crowne; how much more ought wee to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from all fleſhly luſtes which will bring our Soules out of temper; eſpecially conſidering that the Crowne which wee ſtriue for, is incorruptible and everlaſting in Heaven. And this is the true Abſtinence which the Lord requireth at our hands, to abſteine from ſinne, to abſtaine from luſtes, to abſtaine from the workes of the fleſh. Though we ſhould abſtaine eyther from cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine meates never ſo preciſely, or from all meates ſo farre as it is poſſible, yet if we doe not withall abſtaine from ſinne and from the luſts of the fleſh, it is no abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence at all, but rather fond ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>Wherefore beloved, let vs hearken to this couſell of the Apoſtle, and obſerue it in our dayly practiſe, to abſtaine from fleſhly luſtes. Doth our corrupt nature at any time aske any thing at our hands? Let vs deny it, and ſay it nay, and forbeare ſuch deſires. Doth our fleſh ſollicite vs to do or thinke any thing that is againſt our obedience to God? Let vs deny our fleſh, and forbeare all ſuch luſts: Indeede if we were our owne, then might wee iuſtly take our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to our ſelues, and doe what wee liſt; but the Apoſtle 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. Tels vs plainely, that wee are not our owne, but are bought with a price, even with the moſt precious blood of Ieſus Chriſt, and therefore wee muſt bee ruled by him that bought vs becauſe wee are his, and abſtaine from our owne luſts, and deny our owne Fleſh and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, becauſe wee are not our owne. Our Saviour tels vs, wee muſt denie and forſake our ſelues, or els wee are not to follow him, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.23.</p>
            <p>Oh let vs follow him in the regeneration, by abſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from our fleſhly luſts which fight againſt our Soules, and ſo wee ſhall receiue at length the end of our Faith, the ſalvation of our Soules, even that vncorruptible Crowne,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2547:17"/> that Crowne of righteouſneſſe, ſpoken of by the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians chap</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 25. and the ſecond Epiſtle to <hi>Timothie chap</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 8. which the Lord the righteous Iudge, ſhall giue at that day, to all them that loue that his appearing, and is attaineable by, and promiſed onely to thoſe that thus abſtayne from and overcome their fleſhly luſts;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.25. Rom 8.13. Revel. 2.26. Revel. 3.5.</note> which that wee may ſo doe as wee are here exhorted, let vs conclude with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, calling vpon God for the ſpirit of power to enable vs thereunto, and that through Ieſus Chriſt, to whom with God the Father, and the bleſſed Spirit, three diſtinct Perſons, and yet but one God, bee all Honor and Glory, both now and for ever Amen, Amen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2547:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
